<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>security on Kristoffer Lind - Developer, Technologist, Blogger</title><link>https://www.lind.sh/tags/security/</link><description>Recent content in security on Kristoffer Lind - Developer, Technologist, Blogger</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.lind.sh/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Browser defaults are crazy</title><link>https://www.lind.sh/blog/browser-defaults-are-crazy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.lind.sh/blog/browser-defaults-are-crazy/</guid><description>I could use you as a bot to assault web services I dislike, utilize some of your compute to calculate stuff I&amp;rsquo;m interested in or mine cryptocurrencies. I could use it to gather enough information about you that I can recognize you from a different browser or private mode. I could run P2P (peer to peer) software to have you help serve content I want to spread. Oh and how nice of you to leave this tab open for a while before you had time to read it, right?</description></item><item><title>Supply-chain monitoring</title><link>https://www.lind.sh/blog/supply-chain-monitoring/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.lind.sh/blog/supply-chain-monitoring/</guid><description>Software used in this article is locked to specific versions to increase the chance of it working as specified. Make sure you update all of it if you want to actually start using it after experimenting. I&amp;rsquo;ve had this article lying around for a bit before publishing, so versions are pretty outdated even at time of publish.
Automate building inventory specifications for your applications and monitor all those dependencies for known vulnerabilities and license issues.</description></item><item><title>Security automation</title><link>https://www.lind.sh/blog/security-automation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.lind.sh/blog/security-automation/</guid><description>A typical web application involves a lot of code in many layers and manually keeping it secure requires in depth knowledge in all of those layers and lots of maintenance. To increase your chances of keeping it secure you could utilize automation. There are a lot of tools available for helping with security automation and it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty big task to sift through them to find good ones. There are lots and lots of companies selling security tools who wants you on their hook.</description></item><item><title>Running dotnet containers in kubernetes</title><link>https://www.lind.sh/blog/dotnet-containers-in-kubernetes/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.lind.sh/blog/dotnet-containers-in-kubernetes/</guid><description>There are some caveats to running dotnet in containers. You might expect that the docker images you pulled from Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s container registry were checked for vulnerabilities and prepared to run in a containerized environment. If you&amp;rsquo;ve gone with defaults and don&amp;rsquo;t have strict rules on your cluster you&amp;rsquo;ll have an image configured to run alone on a server (which is not a usual setup in a containerized environment) that is also full of known vulnerabilities even when fresh.</description></item></channel></rss>